Good morning, fifth day of the עומר *Omer*, דף ה he, *Daf
Heh* in הוריות *Horayot*. We pick up at the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
at the bottom of דף ד עמוד ב Amud Bais, *Daf Dalet
Amud Bet*, the second משנה Mishna *Mishnah* from the bottom, the second
wide line. And we're still dealing with exactly what is the context
in which a פסק Psak *psak* of בית דין beis din *Beis
Din* leads to them bringing a their special קרבן korban *korban*. So
הורו בית דין beis din שוגגים וכל הקהל Hakahal. שוגגים מביאים פר
mivi'im par, *Horu Beis Din shogegin vechol hakahal shogegin mevi'im par*. So
that's the classic case. They ruled in error, they obviously weren't intentionally
misruling and everybody followed them in error, meaning they weren't טולה בעצמו
*toleh be'atzmo*, they trusted בית דין beis din, *Beis Din* and they
followed בית דין beis din *Beis Din*. That's the example where בית
דין beis din *Beis Din* brings their the cow, the special or
the the bull, the special or I guess it's an ox, whatever.
Anyway, the special sacrifice that they
bring. מזידים ועשו Ve'asu, שוגגים מביאים כשבה ושעירה *Mezidin ve'asu shogegin mevi'im
kisbah use'irah*. So in that case, interestingly, right, here who who should
bring it? The בית דין beis din *Beis Din* was מזיד *mezid*
but you know and everybody else was innocent. So the משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah* says nevertheless, since that doesn't since that doesn't constitute a פסק
*psak* of בית דין beis din *Beis Din*, the individuals bring for
their private sin. So this gets back to that question because you
should sort of object, you said, what do these individuals know? They're
all these these laypeople that trust בית דין beis din, *Beis Din*
just because בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din* decided to be רשעים
*resha'im* and intentionally פסקן *pasken* incorrectly, these poor individuals should have to
bring a קרבן korban *korban*? So once again, this does go back
to this idea that you know that it's not just about being
blame you know being blameworthy, even though they're blameless, they still did
the sin, they bring it, and as long as it can't be
attributed to בית דין Beit Din, *Beis Din*, that's a little ironic,
right, it can't be like the blame can't be like it can't
be sort of seen, well they were just an extension of בית
דין Beit Din *Beis Din*. Why not? בית דין Beit Din. *Beis
Din* was willfully doing this. But nevertheless, since it doesn't really have
that like status as a פסק *psak*, you know, that breaks the
connection. So since that breaks that connection, it's not as if it
were
somehow, you know, attributable to בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din*, which
is a bizarre thing, I still have to tell you. Given if
this given the first משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*, right, that says that they
can be they can be exempt and בית דין Beit Din *Beis
Din* can be exempt and the positions that we've seen before, you
know, that even if בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din* retracts they
could be exempt because in their minds they believe they're following בית
דין Beit Din. *Beis Din*, this is a strange הלכה halacha *halacha*.
But it is consistent with the idea that, you know, it's not
all about blame and if somebody does a sin, a a if
there's a sin done a קרבן korban, *korban* has to be brought.
Now, שוגגים ועשו Ve'asu מזידים *shogegin ve'asu mezidin*. Let's say the בית
דין Beis Din *Beis Din* rules incorrectly and in honest error and
the people willfully sin.
So obviously הרי אלו פטורים *harei elu peturim*, then every you know
then you don't bring a קרבן korban. *korban* if you're a willful
sinner. It's worse, but you don't bring a קרבן korban, *korban*. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. שוגגים ועשו Ve'asu, מזידים
*shogegin ve'asu mezidin*, if the last case of the משנה mishna. *Mishnah*,
בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din* made their ruled in error and
the people went and willfully sinned, הרי אלו פטורים *harei elu peturim*.
So then every you know the sinners are are exempt from a
קרבן korban. *korban*. השוגג דומיא דמזיד *hashogeg dumya demezid*, but would imply
that if they were truly making an error but if it was
a little but but if it wasn't it wasn't a total מזיד
*mezid*, they weren't willfully sinning, but there was an element of מזיד
*mezid* there, it sounds like that in that case חייב Chayav. *chayav*,
then there would still be there would be a קרבן Korban. *korban*.
So והיכי דמי *veheichi dami*, what would be the case where you'd
have a שוגג קרוב למזיד *shogeg karov lemezid*? So it says שהורו
בית דין Beis Din שחלב מותר ונתחלף לו בשומן ואכלו *shehoru Beis
Din shecheilev mutar venischalaf lo beshuman ve'achalo*. So בית דין Beis Din
*Beis Din* made their פסק *psak* that the fat was
forbidden or permissible and this guy was trying to eat the kosher
fat and he ate the טריפה treif! *treifa* fat. So you might
remember that was a case we had at the very first stop.
On the one hand, had he known it was this טריפה treif
*treifa* fat, he would have eaten it anyway because he would have
followed בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din*. But in the in the
actual case, he wasn't following בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din*. He
was trying to eat kosher fat and not the non-kosher fat. Is
that a case where he is considered to be תולה בבית דין
*toleh beBeis Din* and פטור *patur* or תולה בעצמו *toleh be'atzmo* and
חייב chayav *chayav*? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says it sounds like
so there's an element of מזיד *mezid* here, not מזיד *mezid* in
the way that מזיד *mezid* makes it worse, but מזיד *mezid* in
the sense that you're not just fully following בית דין Beis Din
*Beis Din*. You're doing right you're trying to eat the kosher stuff
not the טריפה treif. *treifa* stuff, you're not fully following בית דין
Beis Din. *Beis Din*. So the משנה mishna *Mishnah* says it only
if you're a full מזיד *mezid* are you פטור *patur*. It sounds
like this which is like a partial מזיד *mezid* you'd be חייב
chayav *chayav* that even though you're not fully following בית דין Beis
Din? *Beis Din*, you'd still be חייב chayav. *chayav*. So if that's
true,
so לימא תיפשוט דאיבעיא רמי בר חמא *leima tifshot de'ibaya Rami bar
Chama*, so should this should this be the answer to the question
רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* raised on the first stop, that
in this case
you genuinely are חייב chayav. *chayav* a קרבן Korban, *korban* because you're
not fully following בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din* because you're again
you're not consciously eating the non-kosher fat? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אמר לך משום דתנא רישא מזידים ועשו Ve'asu שוגגים תנא סיפא
שוגגים ועשו v'asu מזידים *amar lach mishum detana reisha mezidin ve'asu shogegin
tana seifa shogegin ve'asu mezidin*. No, the
stylistically the end is Just the mirror image of the beginning. Since
the first case was the בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* was
willful and the people were שוגג *shogeg*, the last case is בית
דין Beis Din, *Beis Din* is שוגג *shogeg* and the people are
willful. But it doesn't mean that any case that's just a hairbreadth
shy of being totally willful that the people would be חייב *chayav*.
That's not true. You could have this case of a middle case
where maybe the people are also פטור *patur* and as we said,
we haven't resolved whether to consider this case where בית דין Beis
Din. *Beis Din* ruled, you innocently sin but not consciously following בית
דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* trying to eat the other thing, whether
that would constitute a case of following בית דין Beis Din. *Beis
Din* to be פטור *patur* or whether that would be a normal
שוגג *shogeg* that you would be חייב *chayav*. So we haven't, that's
the old question which we're not going to resolve based on this
משנה mishna *Mishnah*. Let's go on now to the new משנה mishna
*Mishnah*. הורו בית דין Beis Din. ועשו כל הקהל Hakahal או רובן
על פיהם *Hura Beis Din ve-asu kol ha-kahal o ruban al pi-hem*.
So now we finally get to you have all the criteria for
bringing the קרבן korban. *korban* and now we're going to ask the
question of who brings the קרבן korban? *korban* when it's a wrong
פסק *psak* of בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* and people follow
it. So בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din* gave their פסק *psak*,
everybody listened to them or the majority of the people listened to
them, מביאין פר par *mevi'in par*, then that's the case where they
bring an ox, ובעבודת כוכבים *u-be-avodas kochavim* if they ruled in a
case of עבודה זרה avodah zarah *avoda zara*, מביאין פר ושעיר par
ve'se'ir. *mevi'in par ve-sa'ir*, they bring both an ox for an עולה
*olah* but the חטאת *chatas* in that case is not the ox,
the חטאת *chatas* in that case is a שעיר *sa'ir*. That's because
there are two separate פרשיות Parshiyot, *parshiyos* in the תורה *Torah* which
I'll get to in a minute. Okay, דברי רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir,
*Divrei Rabbi Meir*. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says,
which is I think what we would assume, that then it's the
בית דין Beis Din. *Beis Din*'s responsibility, the בית דין Beis Din
*Beis Din* brings the קרבן korban, *korban*. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah אומר
י"ב שבטים shvatim. מביאין י"ב פרים, עבודת כוכבים מביאין י"ב פרים ושנים
עשר שעירים *Rabbi Yehuda omer yod-beish shevatim mevi'in yod-beish parim, avodas kochavim
mevi'in yod-beish parim u-shenaim asar se'irim*. No, each שבט shevet. *shevet* has
to bring their own קרבן korban. *korban*. So he's sort of disagreeing
in two ways. Obviously number one is he's saying
it's not fundamentally the בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din*'s קרבן korban.
*korban*, it's the ציבור tzibur *tzibbur*'s קרבן korban. *korban*. But you could
have just said the ציבור tzibur *tzibbur* brings one קרבן korban. *korban*,
right, one ox in the case of a normal sin and an
ox for an עולה *olah* and a שעיר *sa'ir* for a חטאת
*chatas* in the case of עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *avoda zara*. Okay,
in addition to shifting it from the בית דין Beis Din *Beis
Din* to the ציבור tzibur *tzibbur*, he's also looking at all of
the tribes as like separate entities. Okay, so each שבט shevet *shevet*
is its own ציבור Tzibur *tzibbur*. All right, so therefore, assuming that
all the tribes sinned, okay, we'll see in a minute what if
not all the tribes sinned, but assuming all the tribes sinned then
each one is its own entity and each one brings the קרבן
korban *korban*. So it's again, it's two points. Number one, it's not
בית דין Beis Din *Beis Din*, it's the ציבור Tzibur *tzibbur*. And
number two, looking at the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* as a confederation of
twelve tribes not as one big unit. That's what he says. Now
the interesting question I think to ask in the position, so we're
going to have a few positions like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah *Rabbi
Yehuda* that the ציבור tzibbur? *tzibbur* brings it, is is the ציבור
tzibbur *tzibbur* bringing it, there's two ways to conceptualize this. One way
to conceptualize this is is the ציבור tzibbur. *tzibbur* bringing it because
the ציבור tzibbur, *tzibbur* sinned? Again, it's not an issue of blame,
but the reality is that the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* did sin. So
if the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* sinned, why do you need בית דין
Beis Din, *Beis Din* to פסקן *pasken*? Why don't you just say
if the majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael. *Klal Yisrael* sins they
bring a special קרבן korban. *korban*? So the answer would be because
if the majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael *Klal Yisrael* sinned without
a פסק *psak* of בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din*, then they're
just sinning as a lot of individuals. Every individual is making a
mistake. Right, in your home you're eating the non-kosher food, in my
home I'm eating the non-kosher food, so it's really just a million
separate individuals, it's not as one unit are we all sinning. Okay,
what happens through the פסק *psak* of בית דין Beis Din. *Beis
Din* is the פסק *psak* of בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din*
gives a common cause for us to be sinning and it unifies
it all as like we are, you know, the head of
כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael, *Klal Yisrael* ruled this way, everybody followed, that
defines our acts and our following as sort of, you know, as
like this, you know, as more of a corporate type of a
sin rather than individual sins. That's one way to conceptualize it. It's
not a קרבן korban, *korban* for the wrong פסק *psak*, it's a
קרבן korban, *korban* for the sin, okay, but you need the בית
דין Beis Din *Beis Din* to define it as a corporate entity
that is sinning rather than a lot of individuals. That's very attractive
to me thinking about it that way. The alternative is to say
that it's being brought for the sin of בית דין Beis Din,
*Beis Din*, but ultimately who's responsible for the sin of בית דין
Beis Din *Beis Din*? The ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur*'s responsible for the sin
of בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din*. It's like when our elected
officials are going off the, you know, are going off the tracks
and are doing terrible things or whatever, who's responsible? Are they responsible
or are we responsible? Right, so that's a different way of looking
at it, that it is for the sin of the wrong פסק
*psak*, but ultimately the ציבור tzibbur. *tzibbur* ultimately bears that responsibility. I
don't like that approach as much. I'd like to more see this
as a fundamental debate between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* and
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah, *Rabbi Yehuda* whereas is it for the פסק
*psak* sin and then it's בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din* brings
it, or is it for the sin of the action which because
of the בית דין beit din *Beis Din* now is a corporate
sin and therefore the people are bringing it.
Yes, isn't the תורה *Torah* from top down rather than a democracy
bottom up?
Right, so since you don't elect the בית דין beit din. *Beis
Din* as much, right, I agree, I totally agree, yes, I totally
agree. Yeah, so you're right. I mean, I didn't spell it out
but yes, one of the reasons I don't like that approach, first
of all is that it shifts, yes, you know, even if to
some degree we all hold responsibility when our elected officials do the
wrong thing, the responsibility starts with them, number one, and number two,
you're absolutely correct, it's not like we elected the בית דין beit
din *Beis Din*, so absolutely. רבי שמעון אומר י"ג פרים Rebbi Shimon
omer yud gimmel parim. *Rabbi Shimon omer yod-gimmel parim*. It's not like
we elected the בית דין. beit din, So absolutely. רבי שמעון אומר
Reb Shimon Omer, י"ג פרים. There are thirteen oxen. ובעבודה זרה כל
אחד עם שלושה עשר פרים. u'be'avodah zarah kol echad im sheloshah asar
parim.
In עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, thirteen פר par וי"ג
שעירים ve'yud gimmel se'irim and thirteen goats. Okay, so he has basically
he combines both positions. Both the ציבור tzibbur brings and the בית
דין beit din brings. Okay, so that's nice. You have both. פר
ושעיר לכל שבט ושבט ופר ושעיר לבית דין. par ve'se'ir le'kol shevet
va'shevet u'far ve'se'ir le'veis din. Fine. הורה בית דין hora beis din
so that's nice three-way debate. הורה בית דין ועשו ז' שבטים או
רובם. hora beis din ve'asu zayin shevatim o rubam. Let's say it's
not let's say it's not all twelve tribes, let's say it's only
seven or the majority of each one of seven על פיהן al
pihen מביאין פר ובעבודה זרה מביאין פר ושעיר דברי רבי מאיר. mevi'in
par u'be'avodah zarah mevi'in par ve'se'ir divrei Rebbi Meir.
So
Rabbi Meir is consistent,
one בית דין's beit din sin.
Once they get the majority of כל ישראל Klal Yisrael to listen
to them, they bring a פר par. and if it's עבודה זרה,
avoda zara. פר par. ושעיר. רבי יהודה אומר ז' שבטים שחטאו מביאין
ז' פרים. Rebbi Yehudah omer zayin shevatim she'chatu mevi'in zayin parim. Okay,
he says no, again, he goes by his position. It's the ציבור
tzibur. who brings, the ציבור tzibur, is defined by the שבט. shevet
So if seven bring, they bring seven cows. Now, here you would
expect him to end there, but now he adds an interesting extra
line: ושאר שבטים שלא חטאו מביאין על ידיהם פר. u'shear shevatim she'lo
chatu mevi'in al yedeihem par. And the other ones that did not
sin bring also a פר. par So he could have just said
they're twelve cows, but the concept, which is what he is saying,
each tribe brings a cow, but conceptually what he is saying is
that they're bringing in a secondary capacity. The prime people that are
responsible are the tribes that sinned. But at the end of the
day it's sort of like כל ישראל ערבים זה בזה. kol Yisrael
areivim zeh ba'zeh. You know, we're all responsible when such a major,
you know, so we but we bear it at a secondary level.
I like it. It's a very nice sort of conceptual point. It's
sort of like what we were discussing before, right? It means, yes,
can the, you know, are the bystanders responsible when somebody does something
wrong? Sure. But the first person who's responsible is the person who
did the thing that's wrong. So like there's enough responsibility to go
around, you know, for everybody to take a piece of it.
But at no point do the individuals of Israel bring? All the
individuals.
Right, correct, correct, because that's what you have.
You'd have a half a million cows.
Right, exactly. Since you have it through the ruling of בית דין,
beit din that unifies it as a corporate sin. So presumably the
על ידיהם, al yedeihem, I imagine what that would mean would be,
I mean the גמרא Gemara. never spells out what it means to
be obligated in this secondary way, but I imagine what it would
mean is that let's say one of the tribes or all the
tribes who sinned are resisting bringing the קרבנות. korbanos. You would not
go and try to demand the קרבנות, korbanos, I'm making this up,
it's not in the גמרא, Gemara but I imagine this, you would
not go and try to demand the קרבן korban. from the secondary
tribe, from the tribes who didn't sin before you actually got the
קרבן korban. from the tribes who did sin. They first have to
own up to their responsibility and once they've owned up to their
responsibility and brought their קרבן, korban, right, then the other tribes also
have some type of a responsibility of, you know, כל ישראל ערבים
זה בזה. kol Yisrael areivim zeh ba'zeh. We're all responsible for one
another and therefore they're bringing as well. Okay.
Also, it reminds me of like the dedication of the מזבח mizbeach
where they all brought the exact same offering. Right, right, but here
they're being brought in to say we're all, we're all connected.
Right. Now, okay. שאף אלו שלא חטאו מביאין על ידי החוטאין. she'af
elu she'lo chatu mevi'in al yedei ha'chotin.
Even though those that didn't sin bringing bringing through those who did
sin. רבי שמעון אומר י"ג פרים ובעבודה זרה י"ג פרים וי"ג שעירים.
Rebbi Shimon omer yud gimmel parim u'be'avodah zarah yud gimmel parim ve'yud
gimmel se'irim. פר ושעיר לכל שבט ושבט ופר ושעיר לבית דין. par
ve'se'ir le'kol shevet va'shevet u'far ve'se'ir le'veis din. Rebbi Shimon does not
agree to this idea that because some sin others have to bring
a קרבן. korban, Okay, and he still fits with his model, though.
So he disagrees with that position of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah and
he still has his model that it's both בית דין beit din
sin, so they bring their one קרבן, korban. and the individual tribe
sin and each tribe brings their קרבן. korban. Now, what's missing here
is the case about if a minority of tribes sin. Because the
משנה Mishnah, doesn't deal with it, the implication would be if it's
only a minority, then like nobody is going to bring. You need
the majority to sin. Okay, בית דין beit din. won't bring because
they didn't have the majority listen. And the individual tribes, even according
to a רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehudah and a רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
approach, might not be bringing if, you know, it's not defined as
כל ישראל Klal Yisrael sins. But that's not so clear, right, because,
you know, maybe even if you focus on the obligation of the
tribes, maybe even a minority of tribes should bring. So the גמרא's
Gemara going to to explore that. What the משנה Mishnah does go
on to discuss is a case where one tribe sins not because
of the בית דין הגדול, beis din ha'gadol, the central authority, but
because of its high court. Okay. הורו בית דין של אחד מן
השבטים ועשה אותו השבט על פיהם. horu beis din shel echad min
ha'shevatim ve'asah oso ha'shevet al pihen. The בית דין beit din, of
one of the tribes gave a ruling and that tribe sinned. Okay,
אותו שבט הוא חייב ושאר כל השבטים פטורים דברי רבי יהודה. oso
shevet hu chayav ve'shear kol ha'shevatim peturim divrei Rebbi Yehudah. So רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda Rabbi Meir would say I don't even want to
discuss it. For Rabbi Meir, it's all the obligation of the בית
דין הגדול, beis din ha'gadol, the Supreme Court of the land. And
in this case, it's an individual tribe thing and of course it's
not in this פרשה parsha and just every individual who sins brings
it. But for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who focused on the obligation
of the tribes, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say I don't
really need it to be a בית דין הגדול. beis din ha'gadol.
If an individual tribe sins, if they just sinned without a בית
דין beit din like I said, then it's just a lot of
individuals sinning. But if they sin through the ruling of their בית
דין, Beit Din, then that makes it a corporate entity. So this
corporate entity of the tribe sinned. And therefore, even it was their
local בית דין Beit Din that unified them, and therefore they bring
their קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
Makes a lot of sense from a רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda approach.
All right. Now he doesn't necessarily say it if the בית דין
הגדול Beit Din Hagadol sinned. בית דין הגדול Beit Din Hagadol which
represents all of כל ישראל, Klall Yisrael, not clear therefore that you
would then focus on individual tribes. That's again still has to be
explored. וחכמים אומרים, V'Chachamim Omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, אין חייבין אלא
על הוראת בית דין הגדול בלבד. Ein Chayavin Ella Al Hora'at Beit
Din Hagadol Bilvad. No, it has to be the big בית דין,
Beit Din שנאמר, Shene'emar, ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו, V'im Kol Adat
Yisrael Yishgu, ולא עדת אותו שבט, V'lo Adat Oto Shevet, not that
tribe. And סתם אחרים Stam Achereim would be רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir
and that makes sense, although this is חכמים Chachamim anyway, but you
could assume that this is רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, because רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is saying it basically focuses on the בית דין הגדול,
Beit Din Hagadol, their sin. But it could even be רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. You could even say, look, even if I focus on
the individual tribes, I'm only going to be through the ruling of
the בית דין הגדול. Beit Din Hagadol. But anyway, רבי יהודה's Reb
Yehuda position certainly makes sense given his position of focusing on the
individual tribes, that to even be the ruling of the local tribe,
of that tribe's local בית דין Beit Din or central בית דין.
Beit Din, Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, ידעו שהורו וטעו מה הורו, Yadu Shehoru Veta'u Mah Horu,
יכל יהיו חייבין. Yachol Yihiyu Chayavin. Now this is a bizarre case,
I can't even begin to understand this.
Okay, בית דין Beit Din paskened wrong, and they realize they made
a mistake, but they didn't realize which thing they made a mistake
about. So the way רש"י Rashi explains this scenario is, they ruled
and they said, they had two rulings, two questions came to them.
One was about a particular type of חלב Chelev of let's say
forbidden fat, and the other was about a particular scenario of דם
Dam of blood. Both of them are איסור כרת. Issur Karet. And
they
said in case X, חלב Chelev is permissible, and in case Y,
the דם Dam is permissible. Okay, and then all of כל ישראל
Klall Yisrael went and they ate the
חלב Chelev of case X and the דם Dam of case Y.
Everybody following? And then בית דין Beit Din realized, oh, one of
those rulings was wrong. Okay, not both of them, one of them
was wrong. So one of them was right, so if it was
the דם Dam that was right, everybody ate the דם, Dam, that
was okay, but then they all ate the חלב, Chelev, they ate
forbidden חלב. Chelev. Or the reverse. We don't remember which one of
those rulings was wrong. Now I don't understand how you can know
you made a wrong ruling and not realize which one of them
was wrong, like I don't understand the scenario. Okay, so anyway, just
let's, we'll just have to go with it. For that's the case.
They, you definitely have the conditions where their wrong פסק led to
all of כל ישראל Klall Yisrael sinning. You just somehow can't remember
whether it was because of the ruling about חלב Chelev or the
ruling about דם. Dam. I mean, I don't, okay, whatever it is.
Anyway, יכל יהיו חייבין, Yachol Yihiyu Chayavin, maybe they'd be חייב. תלמוד
לומר, Talmud Lomar, ונודעה
החטאת, Venoda'a Hachatat, the sin is known, because that they, okay, ולא
שידעו החוטאים. V'lo Sheyadu Hachot'im. It's not sufficient that they know that
they are sinners, they have to know what the sin is, they
have to know what the actual, you know, sin was that was
done. אשר חטאו. Asher Chata'u. Now, now we're going to continue to
do a דרשה, Derasha, going back to more of the theme of
our משנה. Mishnah חטאו שני שבטים מביאים שני פרים. Chata'u Shenei Shevatim
Mevi'im Shenei Parim. The double language of אשר חטאו Asher Chata'u tells
you that if there are two tribes, then they bring two, two
oxen. חטאו שלושה מביאים שלושה. Chata'u Shlosha Mevi'im Shlosha. Okay, which sounds
like a רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda approach of focus on the individual
tribes. או אינו אומר אלא חטאו שני יחידים מביאים שני פרים, חטאו
ג' מביאים ג'. O Eino Omer Ela Chata'u Shenei Yechidim Mevi'im Shenei
Parim, Chata'u Gimmel Mevi'im Gimmel. Maybe and maybe it means maybe in
the case of a בית דין Beit Din. paskening, maybe we should
go that every individual brings a special קרבן, korban, not just every
tribe. תלמוד לומר, Talmud Lomar, הקהל. hakahal It says the congregation. Let
me read you the פרשה Parsha that we're going on, let me
get a חומש. Chumash.
Okay,
so there's two פרשיות, one about עבודה זרה, avoda zara but one
about general. We'll start with the general one. Okay, and it's at
the end of פרשת ויקרא, Parshat Vayikra, towards the end of פרשת
ויקרא. Parshat Vayikra. And it says as follows: it says,
ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו, V'im Kol Adat Yisrael Yishgu, the entire
congregation. Okay, so that's the case that the majority of the people
sin. ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל, V'ne'elam Davar Me'einei Hakahal, something was hidden
from the eyes of the congregation. So the eyes of the congregation
is בית דין. Beit Din They provide the leadership, the eyes.
ועשו, and here's the ועשו in the plural, אחת מכל מצות ה'
אשר לא תעשינה ואשמו, Achat Mikol Mitzvot Hashem Asher Lo Te'asena Ve'ashemu,
and they did one of the things they shouldn't do. ונודעה החטאת,
Venoda'a Hachatat, that's what we started with. The sin becomes known, אשר
חטאו עליה. Asher Chata'u Aleha. והקריבו הקהל, Vehikrivu Hakahal, the הקהל hakahal,
brings. Okay, so we've got a couple of keywords there, right? What
words are the keywords? We
had כל עדת ישראל ישגו, Kol Adat Yisrael Yishgu, okay, that is
the ציבור tzibur. sins, the ציבור tzibur sins.
ונעלם דבר מעיני
הקהל,
Vene'elam Davar Me'einei
HaKahal,
okay, that is בית דין Beit Din ruled incorrectly בשוגג, bishogeg, obviously
that's ונעלם. Vene'elam. Okay.
ונעלם
דבר מעיני הקהל ועשו אחת מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה, Vene'elam
Davar Me'einei HaKahal Ve'asu Achas Mikol Mitzvos Hashem Asher Lo Te'aseina, ועשו,
you know, אחת achas etc. So that's again describing that the ציבור
tzibur sins. Okay.
ונודעה החטאת, Venoda'ah HaChatas,
ונודעה החטאת. Venoda'ah HaChatas.
So they have to become aware
of
the error, and in this case we're saying of the sin and
not the sinners, of the specific error, that is just the point
we just made. Okay,
אשר חטאו עליה הקריבו הקהל. Asher Chatu Aleha Hikrivu HaKahal. And this
is going to be the big one: who brings the קורבן? korban?
Okay, so just to tell you what we're getting up to,
the קהל Kahal brings the קורבן. korban. Who is the קהל? Kahal?
Is the קהל Kahal here בית דין beis din because מעיני הקהל
Me'einei HaKahal means that the בית דין beis din. sinned? Or do
we say no, the eyes of the congregation, בית דין beis din
are the עיניים, einayim, but the קהל Kahal is the community itself.
So who brings the קורבן? korban? Is קהל Kahal here meaning בית
דין beis din, or is קהל Kahal here meaning the ציבור? tzibur
And that's all of the debates in the משנה. Okay, so we're
going to get to that in a minute. Okay, but point number
one was they have to know the specific sin. Okay, so now
we continue. Okay, so it says ועשו in the plural, that's what
we're focusing on right now, means even like two tribes bring true,
bring two.
Maybe it means two individuals in this scenario bring this special קורבן
korban of the פר. par. Okay, וכל
הקהל... תלמוד לומר הקהל הקהל חייב. Vechol HaKahal... Talmud Lomar HaKahal HaKahal
Chayav. So no, we're not talking about individuals. הקריבו הקהל. Hikrivu HaKahal.
We're talking about a tribe. Okay, וכל קהל וקהל חייב. Vechol Kahal
VeKahal Chayav. And every individual קהל, Kahal, not just all of כלל
ישראל. Klal Yisrael? This is obviously a רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda approach,
each individual tribe is obligated.
What's the difference between קהל Kahal and עדה? Edah?
We're not going to discuss that right now. The רב Rav basically
says that עדה Edah is more of a... קהל Kahal is a
more, you know, more shows that they're living up to a higher
level of like... עדה Edah is more has a sense of like
the hoi polloi and the masses, whereas קהל Kahal is a greater
sense of community. But anyway, but that's not the גמרא's Gemara focus.
וכל קהל וקהל חייב. Vechol Kahal VeKahal Chayav. חטאו... Chata... חטאו שני
שבטים מביאים שני פרים. Chatu Shenei Shevatim Mevi'im Shenei Parim.
חטאו זיין מביאים זיין. Chatu Zayin Mevi'im Zayin. ושאר שבטים שלא חטאו
מביאים עליהם פר פר. Ushar Shevatim Shelo Chatu Mevi'im Aleihen Par Par.
Okay, so this is רבי יהודה's Reb Yehuda. clear רבי יהודה Reb
Yehuda position, individual tribes, each tribe brings their own קורבן. korban. Okay,
and here it's explicit by the way, that even if the ruling
is of בית דין הגדול, Beis Din HaGadol, of not of their
individual... of their individual בית דין, beis din, and even if it's
only one or two tribes, they will still bring each tribe on
their own. So for רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda the whole focus on
the individual tribes means that you can have just, you know, you
can start with just one tribe bringing one קורבן korban for its
sin. בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol ruled, everybody else knew better
or whatever didn't have an opportunity, one tribe followed them and listened,
that one tribe brings one קורבן. korban. That's רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda
And then he says, and all the others, ושאר שבטים שלא חטאו
מביאים עליהם פר פר. Ushar Shevatim Shelo Chatu Mevi'im Aleihen Par Par.
The rest all bring their tribe, כאילו אלו שלא חטאו מביאים על
ידי החוטאים. K'afilu Elu Shelo Chatu Mevi'im Al Yedei HaChotim. Okay, now
the question that's ambiguous about רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda? is when he
says the other tribes bring as a result of the tribe... of
the tribes that actually sinned, is that only referring to his case
when he says seven tribes bring, when you have a majority? If
the majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael, sinned, then we all really
have to own that responsibility, or is he even talking about a
case where an individual tribe sinned? The גמרא Gemara is going to
ask that when we get to the עמוד ב, it's a little
ambiguous right now. ולכך נאמר קהל לחייב על כל קהל וקהל דברי
רבי יהודה. Velach Ne'emar Kahal Lechayev Al Kol Kahal VeKahal Divrei Reb
Yehuda. So that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, קהל Kahal here
means every individual tribe. Okay, רבי שמעון Reb Shimon אומר, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon, says זיין שבטים שחטאו מביאים זיין פרים ובית דין מביאים
עליהם פר. Zayin Shevatim Shechatu Mevi'im Zayin Parim U-Beis Din Mevi'im Aleihen
Par. שנאמר למטה... Shene'emar Lemata... okay so he says... so he disagrees
in two ways. Number one, the most important disagreement is he says
it's both the קהל, Kahal, both the sinners bring one קורבן korban
for their corporate sin, and the בית דין beis din, brings a
קורבן, korban, you know, a פר for its sin. So it's both
the ציבור and the בית דין. beis din The other way he
disagrees is he doesn't buy into this secondary קורבן. korban. Only those
who sin bring the קורבן. korban. Okay.
Now how do you get it that both the קהל Kahal and
the בית דין? beis din, שנאמר למטה קהל ונאמר למעלה קהל. Shene'emar
Lemata Kahal Vene'emar Lemala Kahal. מה קהל האמור למעלה בית דין עם
הקהל. Ma Kahal Ha'amur Lemala Beis Din Im HaKahal. So here the
word מעיני הקהל, Me'einei HaKahal, the עיניים einayim is בית דין beis
din. and the קהל Kahal is the ציבור. So here the word
קהל Kahal comes in the context of בית דין. beis din. So
therefore when it says קהל Kahal down here, yes, קהל Kahal means
the ציבור, but since up here it's the ציבור's connected to the
בית דין, Beis Din, down here the ציבור is also connected to
the בית דין. Beis Din. And therefore the people who are obligated
in the קורבן korban are both the ציבור and the בית דין.
Beis Din, And the בית דין. Beis Din Okay, אמר למעלה בית
דין עם קהל אף כאן אמור למטה בית דין עם קהל. Amar
lemalah beis din im kahal, af kan amur lematah beis din im
kahal. So that's רבי שמעון'ס Rebbi Shimon's position, both. רבי מאיר אומר,
Rebbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says ז' שבטים שחטאו בית
דין מביאים על ידיהם פר ואין פטורין. Zayin shevatim shechatu beis din
mivi'im al yadeihem par ve'ein paturin. The only obligation is the בית
דין. Beis Din, And you need obviously the majority of the ציבור.
Okay, נאמר קהל למטה ונאמר קהל למעלה. Ne'emar kahal lematah vene'emar kahal
lemalah. It says קהל kahal twice. מה קהל האמור למעלה בית דין
ולא ציבור, Ma kahal hamur lemalah beis din velo tzibbur, he says
I don't divide these words. מעיני הקהל Me'einei hakahal means the בית
דין. So this literally means the eyes of the community and the
community is the community. But the קהל kahal word here is in
the context of בית דין. So this קהל kahal is echoing this
entire phrase. והקריבו הקהל Ve'hikrivu hakahal here means מעיני הקהל. me'einei hakahal.
Those that represent the community, this is talking about בית דין. Okay?
So אף קהל האמור למטה בית דין ולא ציבור. Af kahal ha'amur
lematah beis din velo tzibbur. That's his position. רבי שמעון אלעזר אומר
משמו, Rebbi Shimon Elazar omer mishmo, רבי שמעון אלעזר Rebbi Shimon Elazar
says in the name of רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir חטאו ששה שבטים
ואין רובו של קהל או ז' אף על פי שאין רובו של
קהל. Chatu shishah shevatim ve'ein rubo shel kahal o zayin af al
pi she'ein rubo shel kahal. Let's say you only have a majority
defined through one measure. This gets back again to like, you know,
the popular vote versus the electoral college. Okay? You either have seven
tribes but you don't have the popular vote, you don't have the
majority of the people, or you have the majority of the people
but you only have six tribes. Okay? In that case, מביאים פר,
mivi'im par. מביאים פר.
That would suffice. That suffices to constitute a sense of the majority.
The majority of the people would be defined as by either measure.
Okay. By the way, if the seven—I mean this is just like
we have in our elections—if the seven—if you go by the seven
tribes even though they're not the majority, you could actually have just
like, you know, twenty-six percent or something of the people, right? None
of the other tribes do it at all. And of those seven
tribes only a majority of those tribes—it wouldn't be twenty-six, it would
be a little more. Actually, since we don't—they don't even have—it's not
based on the population, it's not based on like the representatives, you
know, it's not like their number of electoral votes, each one—it's—each one
gets one essentially, you could even have smaller than twenty-six percent. You
could take the seven smallest tribes and just have the majority of
the seven smallest tribes, you know, ten percent of the ציבור if
it worked out correctly could lead to bringing this קרבן. korban. Okay,
anyway. אמר מר, Amar mar,
now we're going to unpack that ברייתא braisa we just read. ונודעה
החטאת ולא שידעו החוטא. Venoda hachattas velo sheyad'u hachotei. מאן תנא, Man
tanna, who is this one that makes a—that says that if you
don't know the sin itself, you don't bring a קרבן? korban? So
רב יהודה אמר רב ואיתימא רבא, Rav Yehuda amar Rav ve'i teima
Rava, דלא כרבי אליעזר. delo k'Rebbi Eliezer. It's not like רבי אליעזר,
Rebbi Eliezer, as we said. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rebbi Eliezer, this
is about a case about an individual. Somebody ate something wrong. Somebody
had in front of him some food and he ate it. בשוגג,
Beshogeg, he thought it was כשר. kosher. And somebody said, "Ah, that
was טריפה!" He says, "Oh my God, what type of טריפה was
it?" He says, "I don't know, it was either חלב cheilev or
דם." dam. Okay, I knew I put one of those on the
table and you just went ahead and ate it. So you definitely
did a sin that you're חייב a קרבן, korban but we don't
know what sin you did. Okay? So רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says
מה נפשך, ma nafishach, what difference should it make? Bring a קרבן.
korban אם חלב אכל
חייב נותר חייב. Im cheilev achal achayav, nosar achayav. So he didn't
have חלב cheilev ודם, v'dam, חלב ונותר. cheilev venosar. Whatever it is
that you ate, you're חייב a קרבן. korban? So even if you
don't know what the specific sin was, you should bring a קרבן.
korban רבי
יהושע—so Rebbi Yehoshua therefore, according to רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, in our
case too, בית דין should bring a קרבן. korban You don't have
to know the individual sin. רב אשי אמר אפילו תימא רבי אליעזר,
Rav Ashi amar afilu teima Rebbi Eliezer, even רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
could agree to our משנה. שאני הכא דכתיב אשר חטאו עליה. Shani
hacha de'chsiv asher chatu aleha. Okay, ונודעה החטאת venoda hachattat I didn't
end it.
אשר חטאו עליה. Asher chatu aleha. So אשר חטאו עליה asher chatu
aleha is very specific that you need to know the exact sin.
And therefore even רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that would say by an
individual you don't need to know the exact sin, here he would
say you do have to.
What about it be תלוי taluy if it's not certain?
No, because you're certain, you definitely did a sin, you definitely ate
something טריפה.
תלוי Taluy is only when you're
not sure if you did a sin at all, right? Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara? says התם נמי הכתיב אשר חטא בה. Hatam nami
hachsiv asher chata bah. So what? By an individual קרבן korban? it
also says the sin wherewith you sinned. It also specific about emphasizing
the sin itself and nevertheless רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says his position.
The גמרא Gemara says no, there רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer could use
that phrase to say something else. הוא מיבעי ליה פרט למתעסק. Hu
miba'ei lei perat le'misaseik. That's telling you that you have to actually
be involved in the sin itself and not just do the sin
act like in a complete accidental way, meaning like you know you're
walking by a light switch and you accidentally turn on the light
on שבת. Shabbos. You're trying to pick up you know some keys
that fell on the ground and you accidentally pull out some grass.
That you're not directly involved in the sin itself, it's incidental, and
that's what אשר חטא בה asher chata bah excludes. Okay, so there
you don't have an extra phrase to say you need the sin—to
know the sin itself, but here the גמרא Gemara says even רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer could agree you have to know the sin itself.
Okay, that was like a little parenthetical. מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai
ta'ama de'Rebbi Yehuda? Now, let's get back to this idea about who
brings the קרבן. korban? So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? says each individual
tribe brings the קרבן, korban, even a single tribe brings the קרבן,
korban, and he also has this idea of a גרירה, gurerah, but
he does not have that בית דין brings the קרבן. korban So
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'ama de'Rebbi Yehuda? What's the reason of
רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda קסבר... Kasavar... Now, let's get back to this
idea about who brings the קרבן. korban. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
says each individual tribe brings the קרבן, even a single tribe brings
the קרבן, and he also has this idea of גרירה, grira, but
he does not have the בית דין brings the קרבן. Okay. So
מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai tama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the reason of
רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda. קסבר ארבע קהלי כתיב. Kasavar arba kahali ksiv.
ארבע קהלי כתיב. Arba kahali ksiv. It says קהל kahal four times.
I mean, it really says it twice, but הקהל hakahal. is like
a separate mention. So we have four קהלים kahals to play with.
Okay, קהל, הקהל, kahal hakahal... קהל, kahal, הקהל. hakahal, חד לחייב על
כל קהל וקהל, Chad l'chaiva al kol kahal v'kahal, one of the
קהלים kahals is telling you that each individual tribe is obligated, so
you would bring twelve קרבנות korbanos if all twelve tribes. וחד להוראה
תלויה בבית דין ומעשה תלויה בקהל. V'chad l'hora'ah tluyah b'Beis Din u'ma'aseh
tluya b'kahal.
One is to tell you, you know, that, well I don't know
where you get it in the context, but one to tell you
that it's the קהל kahal, is the one that does the sin,
בית דין is the one that
פוסק. paskens. וחד לגרירה, V'chad l'grira, one to tell you that once
some of the tribes bring, the other tribes will bring as well.
וחד לשבט שעשה על פי בית דינו. V'chad l'shevet she'asah al pi
Beis Dino. And the other is to tell you the idea that
even if it wasn't a בית דין הגדול, Beis Din haGadol, once
we're focusing on individual tribes, even if a tribe follows just its
own בית דין, its own central court, that also is enough. Okay,
so that's where he gets all the different חידושים chidushim of his
approach from this high emphasis on קהל. kahal And that tells him
all of these aspects that are all about the ציבור. Okay, גרירה,
grira, the individual tribe, and so on.
Okay, ורבי שמעון, v'Rabbi Shimon, now רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon. who agrees
with him general that it's the, well who agrees that there is
an element of the individual tribe, but also sees an idea of
בית דין, and he doesn't agree with these other two ideas. He
doesn't agree with גרירה grira that if some tribes bring it the
other bring, and he doesn't agree with the idea of an individual
tribe with its own בית דין. You still need an idea of
a central בית דין, and you probably still need the idea of
a majority of tribes.
רבי שמעון תלתא קהלי כתיבי. Rabbi Shimon tlata kahali ksivi. It says
it three times effectively. הקהל, hakahal. קהל, kahal. הקהל. hakahal, מעיני הקהל,
Me'einei hakahal, the fact here that we had a ה, he okay,
we don't get to count this ה he as an extra mention,
why? אורחיה דקרא הוא, Orchei d'kra hu, כדאמרי אינשי, k'd'amri inshi, מעיני
דפלניא. me'einei d'planya. The eyes of so-and-so. You needed the word הקהל,
hakahal. it would not be grammatical to say מעיני קהל. me'einei kahal.
You needed the ה he here, so the ה he, doesn't get
to count as an extra mention. So this counts as one mention
and this counts as two. Okay. חד לחייב על כל קהל וקהל.
Chad l'chaiva al kol kahal v'kahal.
So one is to tell you this idea again that it goes
by the individual
tribes, okay, that is true. ותרי אחריני, v'trei achrini, now the other
two are: נאמר למטה קהל ונאמר למעלה קהל מה להלן בית דין
עם קהל אף כאן בית דין עם קהל. ne'emar l'mata kahal v'ne'emar
l'mala kahal ma hallan Beis Din im kahal af kan Beis Din
im kahal. The other two are to create this link and to
say that it's the בית דין's obligation together with the קהל. kahal,
So one קהל kahal. extra קהל kahal as it were, let's say
the ה, he is coming to tell you that there is an
obligation on the קהל kahal itself. Okay, and each separate tribe, not
just on the קהל kahal as a ציבור, one for all of
כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael כל קהל וקהל, kol kahal v'kahal, every separate
tribe. So one of these extra קהלים kahals as it were is
to tell you there's an idea of every separate tribe. But beyond
that, we just link the two and we say, okay, every separate
tribe plus בית דין, and those are the two basic components of
his position and he doesn't have the idea of a קהל kahal
with its own בית דין and he doesn't have an idea of
גרירה. grira. That's רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon Okay,
ורבי מאיר, v'Rabbi Meir, קהל kahal הקהל... hakahal לא דריש. lo darish.
He doesn't buy into this extra ה and that there's extra words
to interpret. הילכך תרי קהלי כתיבי. Hilkach trei kahali ksivi. He only
focuses on the fact that it says קהל kahal here and it
says קהל kahal here. ומיבעי ליה לנאמר למטה קהל ונאמר למעלה קהל
מה להלן בית דין ולא ציבור אף כאן בית דין ולא ציבור.
u'mibai lei l'ne'emar l'mata kahal v'ne'emar l'mala kahal ma hallan Beis Din
v'lo tzibor af kan Beis Din v'lo tzibor. And for him, he
focuses on this מעיני הקהל me'einei hakahal to say בית דין, and
he links it down here and he says it's all one thing,
it's all בית דין, that's the basic point. Okay, so now we've
mapped their different positions onto the פסוקים. psukim. Okay. ורבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, v'Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, now ורבי שמעון בן אלעזר v'Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar who has his weird idea, not weird idea, his interesting
idea that majority could be counted by one of two measures. So
מאי טעמא? mai tama? כתיב והיה אם מעיני
העדה. ksiv v'haya im me'einei ha'eidah. Here's עדה. eidah. This is by
the case where it says it by the עבודה זרה. avoda zara,
Okay, so the פרשה parsha by עבודה זרה avoda zara coming at
the end of שלח Shlach says: וכי
תשגו ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה אשר דבר ה' אל
משה. v'chi
tishgu v'lo ta'asu es kol hamitzvos ha'eileh asher diber Hashem
el Moshe.
So you don't do all the מצות. mitzvos. So all the מצות
mitzvos is read as you don't do עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah. you
violate in a sense all the מצות. mitzvos. עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah.
represents that. את כל אשר צוה ה' אליכם ביד משה מן היום
אשר צוה ה' והלאה לדורותיכם. es kol asher tziva Hashem aleichem b'yad
Moshe min hayom asher tziva Hashem v'hal'ah l'doroseichem. והיה אם מעיני העדה
נעשתה לשגגה. v'haya im me'einei ha'eidah ne'estah l'shgaga.
So notice here a similar language, okay, מעיני העדה, me'einei ha'eidah, not
מעיני הקהל, me'einei hakahal, but מעיני העדה. me'einei ha'eidah. נעשתה לשגגה. ne'estah
l'shgaga. ועשו כל העדה פר בן בקר
אחד
לעולה.
v'asu kol ha'eidah par ben bakar
echad l'olah. And
ועשו here is the קרבן. פר בן בקר אחד לעולה. par ben
bakar echad l'olah. Okay, so ועשו כל העדה פר בן בקר אחד
לעולה. v'asu kol ha'eidah par ben bakar echad l'olah.
So that's the פר. אחד par echad. לעולה, לריח ניחוח לה' ומנחתו
ונסכו ושעיר עזים אחד לחטאת. l'reiach nichoach l'Hashem u'minchaso v'nisko u'se'ir izim
echad l'chatas. וכיפר הכהן. v'chiper hacohen. ושעיר עזים אחד
לחטאת.
u'se'ir izim echad
l'chatas.
Okay, sorry. What do we have back to the גמרא? Gemara So
where does רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar get his
idea that you could measure the רוב rov in one of two
ways? So כתיב והיה אם מעיני העדה. ksiv v'hayah im me'einei ha'edah.
אמר מיעוטא דכתיב מעיני. amar miuta d'chsiv me'einei. The מ mem מעיני.
me'einei.
I don't know why he doesn't have the מ mem here of
מעיני הקהל, me'einei hakahal, but the מ mem means not the entirety,
from a portion of it. Okay, there's an element of a minority.
ודכתיב לכל העם בשגגה. u'dechsiv l'chol ha'am bishgaga. The end of this
is לכל העם. l'chol ha'am. Okay, למימרא דרובא אין, מיעוטא לא. l'meimra
d'rubba in, miuta lo. So לכל העם l'chol ha'am means you need
a majority. So one verse implies the majority, one verse implies even
a minority. הכיצד? hakeitzad? So the point is any, even if you
have one measure that's a minority, as long as the other measure's
a majority you're okay. עשו ו' והן רובו של קהל, או ז'
אף על פי שאינן רובו של קהל, חייבין. asu vav v'hen rubo
shel kahal, o zayin af al pi she'einan rubo shel kahal, chayavin.
Of course one would like to know, according to רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, what if you had עשו ה' דרובו
של קהל? asu heh d'rubo shel kahal? Why does he only give
the example that you have six that's a majority, right? You should
give a real minority of tribes, but anyway. Okay, רבי שמעון ורבי
מאיר, Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi Meir, so those map their positions onto the
פסוקים. psukim. רבי שמעון ורבי מאיר: הוראה תלויה בבית דין, ומעשה תלויה
בקהל, מנא להו? Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi Meir: hora'ah tluya b'veit din, u'ma'aseh
tluya b'kahal, mna l'hu?
So where does רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar and
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, know the idea, רבי שמעון ורבי מאיר Rabbi
Shimon v'Rabbi Meir know the idea that the מעשה ma'aseh is תלויה
בקהל, tluya b'kahal, that the בית דין is the one that does
the paskening and the קהל kahal is doing the one that's sinning?
Because if you remember, רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda learned it from the
extra word of הקהל. That only הקהל are the sinners. You measure
the sin by the קהל, kahal, not by the בית דין. Okay,
how do רבי מאיר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Shimon who don't
have an extra קהל, kahal, where do they learn that idea? Maybe
according to them, בית דין also would have to sin in order
for you would have to do the sin itself in order to
bring a קרבן. So אמר אביי דאמר קרא: והיה אם מעיני העדה
נעשתה לשגגה. amar Abaye d'amar kra: v'hayah im me'einei ha'edah ne'esta lishgaga.
So now we are going to use this פסוקים psukim by עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah, נעשתה לשגגה ne'esta lishgaga means, here you have the
בית דין, the מעיני העדה, me'einei ha'edah, and נעשתה ne'esta means it
was done by others, not done by them. So this shows you
the בית דין does the ruling and the others do the sinning.
You don't need the בית דין to do the sinning. Okay, רבא
אמר: מ'לכל העם בשגגה'. Rava amar: mi'lchol ha'am bishgaga. The end of
that פרשה. parsha. The people have the שגגה. shgaga. העם ha'am is
בשגגה. bishgaga. They're the ones with the actual sin. You don't need
the בית דין to have done the sin in practice. וצריכא. u'tzricha.
And you need both of those. אי כתב רחמנא: והיה אם מעיני
העדה נעשתה לשגגה, הוה אמינא אפילו מיעוטא. ei ksav Rachmana: v'hayah im
me'einei ha'edah ne'esta lishgaga, hava amina afilu miuta. If it just said
it was done, you wouldn't have had the idea that the majority
of the people sinned. להכי כתיב: לכל העם בשגגה. l'hachi ksiv: l'chol
ha'am bishgaga. The entire people, to tell you that the majority of
the people did the sin. ואי כתב: לכל העם בשגגה, הוה אמינא
עד דעבדי בית דין בהדיה. v'ei ksiv: l'chol ha'am bishgaga, hava amina
ad d'avdi beit din bahadei. Maybe בית דין would have to do
the sin as well. להכי כתיב: והיה אם מעיני העדה נעשתה לשגגה.
l'hachi ksiv: v'hayah im me'einei ha'edah ne'esta lishgaga. It was done, not
by them. והא כי כתיבי הני קראי בעבודה זרה כתיבי. v'ha ki
ksivi hanei krai b'avodah zarah ksivi. We just see it's all very
nice, but all that's by עבודה זרה. How do you know to
apply that to our case, which is a normal sin? ילפינן מעיני
מעיני. yalfinan me'einei me'einei. You have the מעיני me'einei here and you
have the מעיני me'einei there. So this basically helps bring in all
the relevant פסוקים psukim and showing how they're parallel cases except this
is עבודה זרה, so it's a slightly different קרבן, but nevertheless the
criteria are the same and you can even learn some criteria one
from the next. Okay, הורו בית דין של אחד. horu beit din
shel echad. Now we get to the idea of an individual tribe's
בית דין. איבעיא להו. iba'ya l'hu. They raised the question. שבט אחד
לרבי יהודה בהורו בית דין הגדול, מי מייתו שאר שבטים אטויה? shevet
echad l'Rabbi Yehuda b'horu beit din hagadol, mi maitu shear shvatim atuya?
This was what was ambiguous by the earlier ברייתא. braita. You had
the בית דין הגדול, beit din hagadol, so that's a unifying factor,
and you have one שבט shevet. sin, not seven שבטים. shvatim If
it's one שבט shevet sin with its own בית דין, they bring
and everybody else doesn't. There's no sense of some corporate responsibility. But
right, that was clear for רבי יהודה. Reb Yehuda If it was
he never mentioned the idea of the other שבטים shvatim if it
was just the local בית דין of one שבט. shevet But if
it's the בית דין הגדול beit din hagadol and one שבט shevet
sinned, would that create enough of a responsibility on the other שבטים
shvatim to bring קרבנות korbanot as well even if it's not the
majority of שבטים shvatim, that are sinning? And that was unclear from
earlier sources, the earlier ברייתות braitos and משניות mishnayos of רבי יהודה.
Reb Yehuda Okay, שבט אחד לרבי יהודה בהורו בית דין הגדול, מי
מייתו שאר שבטים אטויה? shevet echad l'Rabbi Yehuda b'horu beit din hagadol,
mi maitu shear shvatim atuya? Do the other tribes bring or not?
So מי אמרינן שבעה שבטים הוא דמייתו שאר שבטים בהדייהו? mi amrinan
shiva shvatim hu d'maitu shear shvatim bahadeihu? So when seven tribes sin,
then the other tribes bring with them. Why? משום דאיכא רובא. mishum
d'ika rubba. Because in the end of the day there's a majority
of שבטים, so that creates a responsibility we all have to bear
that responsibility. אבל חד שבט דליכא רובא לא. aval chad shevet d'leika
rubba lo. But an individual שבט shevet does not bear that responsibility.
You know, that's like that's their issue. Why does that translate into
a responsibility of all of כלל ישראל? Klal Yisrael Okay, so that's
a logical position. או דלמא, o dilma, or should we say, לא
שנא, lo shena, it doesn't matter, an entire שבט shevet did it,
it's all of our responsibility. Okay, so תא שמע, ta shma, come
and hear. מה הן מביאין? פר אחד. רבי שמעון אומר: שני פרים.
ma hen mevi'in? par echad. Rabbi Shimon omer: shnei parim. What do
they bring? פר אחד. one ox. Rabbi Shimon says two. So that's
very nice, we'd like to know what the circumstances are. So במאי
עסקינן? Bemaei askinan? What's the case? אי לימא משחטאו שבע, Iy leima
meshachatu shiva, so seven, so then you understand that the, you know,
it's a classic case of the majority sins and תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma would be Rabbi Meir and say one cow, brought by בית
דין, and Rabbi Shimon would say one by בית דין and one
by the ציבור. There's only one little problem. Rabbi Shimon says eight.
Okay? You could have a conceptual position that would say two. We,
you know, that would sort of say the ציבור we always look
at the entire ציבור not in terms of its tribes, but in
terms of one big כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael. but we haven't had
that position in any of the Tannaic sources. Anybody that says the
ציבור brings as an individual entity. Okay? So if that's the case,
it would be eight. So אי לימא משחטאו שבע, Iy leima meshachatu
shiva, Rabbi Shimon תמניא בעי. tamanya baei. He would require eight. אלא
דחטא שבט אחד, Ella dechata shevet echad, one tribe sinned. Okay? And
then you could, so now, so then the גמרא Gemara says במאי?
Bemaei? Now what's the case? אי באוראת בית דינו, Iy be'ora'at Beit
Dino, if it's its own local בית דין that ruled, Rabbi Shimon
לית ליה. Rabbi Shimon leit lei. Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold the idea
that a local בית דין would, would lead to the bringing of
a special קרבן. אלא באוראת בית דין הגדול, Ella be'ora'at Beit Din
HaGadol, with the ruling of the בית דין הגדול. Beit Din HaGadol.
Now I should mention that Rabbi Shimon never said that if the
בית דין הגדול Beit Din HaGadol ruled and one tribe sinned that
that one tribe brings. Rabbi Shimon only spoke in scenarios where the
majority brought. But it's logical to assume that he would say that
since at the end of the day, he has the idea that
individual tribes bring. So maybe individual tribes bring even if it's only
one or two tribes. Okay? Why do you need everybody to sin
in order for the individual tribe to bring its קרבן? So that
would explain why Rabbi Shimon would say two. You have בית דין
הגדול Beit Din HaGadol ruling and one tribe sinning, so one, one
קרבן for one tribe, one קרבן for בית דין הגדול. Beit Din
HaGadol. Okay.
ותנא קמא מאן? VeTanna Kamma man? Now who's the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma that says in that case it's only one קרבן? אי נימא
רבי מאיר, Iy neima Rabbi Meir, if it's Rabbi Meir, הרוב בעי,
HaRov baei, Rabbi Meir who focuses on the בית דין הגדול, Beit
Din HaGadol, he would require the majority of the tribes to sin.
אלא לאו רבי יהודה. Ella lav Rabbi Yehuda. So the only remaining
position, we've got one tribe sinning, Rabbi Shimon says it's two קרבנות
korbanot for the tribe and for בית דין, so logically now it's
Rabbi Yehuda that would say it's one קרבן just for the tribe.
Okay, but why is it only one? What about the other tribes?
So אמרי, Amri, so therefore it seems to be a good proof,
I mean it's reading a lot in but it seems to be
the case that fits, that for Rabbi Yehuda, if one tribe sinned,
it's only one קרבן and the other tribes don't bring as a
result of that one tribe. So אמרי, Amri, so doesn't that prove
that for Rabbi Yehuda they do not bring in that case? No,
maybe that's not the scenario. אמרי הכא במאי עסקינן, Amri hacha bemaei
askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שחטאו ששה שבטים והן רוב
שבקהל, Kegon shechatu shisha shevatim vehen rov shebakhal, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
היא, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar hi, דתניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר
משמו, Detanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer mishmo, חטאו ששה והן רוב
שבקהל או שבעה אף על פי שאינן רוב שבקהל מביאים פר. Chatu
shisha vehen rov shebakhal o shiva af al pi she'einan rov shebakhal
mevi'im par. Maybe it's the special case of this mixed minority majority.
And in that type of a case, you know, Rabbi Shimon would
say you bring one. Now because again, Rabbi Shimon is really following
a Rabbi Meir position that says that that counts enough of a
majority that you would bring a, that the בית דין would bring.
Okay, so now, but that's very good, but what's Rabbi Shimon's case?
Okay, so let's just here rewrite this.
That makes sense, and then Rabbi Shimon says one. Right.
So the חכמים Chachamim say one, and Rabbi Shimon says two. Okay,
so one version of this is it's one
tribe that sinned and the חכמים Chachamim is Rabbi Yehuda and he
would say one, and Rabbi Shimon would say two because it's one
for בית דין and one for the tribe.
Okay, that's one way of understanding it. But then you have a
case if it's one tribe and you're bringing, you don't say גררא.
grara. That would prove our point that you would not have the
other tribes responsible if it's only one tribe. Okay, then that's a
reasonable read of it. Now we're suggesting a different read. The different
read is six plus רוב rov or seven
plus מיעוט. mi'ut. Okay, that's the, you know, the special mixed case
of Rabbi Shimon. So the חכמים Chachamim here would say, right, the
חכמים Chachamim would be basically who's the חכמים? Chachamim? That would be
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar and they say one for בית דין. Is
it one for the tribe? That's enough of a case of a
majority for the בית דין to bring. Okay, we get that, we
get why the חכמים Chachamim there would be saying one, that this
constitutes a majority for בית דין to bring. But you still have
Rabbi Shimon saying two. Now why is Rabbi Shimon saying two? Shouldn't
Rabbi Shimon be saying like eight or seven? Right? Doesn't Rabbi Shimon
go by this idea that you sort of count all of this
as a, you know, as multiple tribes? So this becomes now very
bizarre. Now what you have to assert for, for this idea is
when does Rabbi Shimon say that the individual tribes, this is what
I was sort of saying the... measured by both measures. If you
have a majority then each individual tribe brings, that's only when you
have the majority. And now we would be saying only the majority
measured by both measures. If you have a majority then each individual
tribe brings. But if you have some mix of majority and minority
it's a strange idea. I can't really understand it. In that case,
then רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would be saying one for all the
tribes.
Which
is a very bizarre idea, right? Why? Because it's this mixed majority
minority, do you have one and you clump them all together, but
when it's literally a majority by multiple measures, then each tribe stands
by itself. Okay? It's somehow this mix pulls them all together as
one unit. Okay, so that's a very strange reading. Almost the Senate.
Yeah, something like that.
Wouldn't it make sense I think the case is talking about one
שבט shevet that constitutes I don't know 51 percent of the עדה?
edah?
Oh, that would be a nice way of explaining.
Then that works for רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah, that's what רש"י Rashi says. But it's a nice way of
explaining it. Once you have that mix, you could say one שבט
shevet the majority of the עדה, edah, so therefore one thing for
בית דין and for him you get the one שבט shevet plus
בית דין. Yeah, רש"י Rashi must mean רש"י Rashi literally exactly. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. But that's a very nice read of it, you know?
So yes, that could be a very nice read. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, but that's a way of
getting out of that ברייתא, braisa, although the simple reading of the
ברייתא braisa worked very well to say for רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda,
you don't say גרירה greira for one tribe.
Okay, let's try again.
תא שמע, Tashma, end of the first wide line. רבי יהודה אומר
שבט שעשה בהוראת בית דינו, Reb Yehuda omer shevet she’asa b’oras beis
dino, if a שבט shevet follows its court, אותו שבט חייב ושאר
כל השבטים פטורין. oso shevet chayav v’shaar kol shevatim peturin. That שבט
shevet brings and the other ones don't. ובהוראת בית דינו הגדול, U'v’oras
beis dino hagadol, אפילו שאר שבטים חייבין. afilu shaar shevatim chayavin. But
if that one tribe sins based on the rule of the בית
דין הגדול, beis din hagadol, then the other tribes bring as well.
So that's an explicit statement. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, is very clear
you say גרירה greira even when an individual tribe brings. We’re always
responsible for one another. If one tribe brings, the other tribes are
responsible. שמע מינה, Shma mina, so that's an explicit proof. Okay. אמר
רב אשי מתניתין נמי דייקא, Amar Rav Ashi matnisin nami dika, this
also can be discovered by a close read of our משנה that
this is essentially רבי יהודה’s Rebbi Yehuda, position. דתני, Detani, because our
משנה says ועשה אותו שבט על פיהם, v’asa oso shevet al pihem,
when in the case of our משנה where the local, where the
שבט’s shevet בית דין ruled, it says that שבט shevet followed, אותו
שבט חייב ושאר כל השבטים פטורין. oso shevet chayav v’shaar kol shevatim
peturin. That שבט shevet brings and everybody else is exempt. למה לי
למיתני ושאר שבטים פטורין? Lama li lemisni v’shaar shevatim peturin? Why did
he have to say all the other tribes are exempt? הא תנא
אותו שבט חייב, Ha tana oso shevet chayav, just say that שבט
shevet is חייב. Of course if you say that one it means
not the others.
וכיון דתניא אותו שבט חייב ממילא ידענא דשאר שבטים פטורין, V’keivan detanya
oso shevet chayav mimila yadana she’shaar shevatim peturin, obviously the other ones
are exempt. אלא הא קמשמע לן, Ela ha kameshmalan, what it's telling
me is דבהוראת בית דינו, d’b’oras beis dino, when it's the local
tribe's בית דין, הוא דשאר שבטים פטורין, hu d’shaar shevatim peturin, that's
when the other tribes are off the hook. אבל בהוראת בית דינו
הגדול, Aval b’oras beis dino hagadol, אפילו שאר שבטים חייבין, afilu shaar
shevatim chayavin, but the ruling of the main בית דין, even the
other ones are חייב. שמע מינה. Shma mina. That's a very nice
דיוק. diyuk. Okay, and now we know for רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda
he holds this idea that the other tribes have responsibility even if
just one tribe is bringing as long as it's a ruling of
the בית דין הגדול. beis din hagadol. The בית דין הגדול beis
din hagadol makes it a כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael type of an
event. If it's your local בית דין, your local בית דין is
going off the skids. Okay, your local, you know whatever, you know
state is acting is following its own weird weird idea, but if
it's something that's coming from you know from the בית דין הגדול,
beis din hagadol, the Supreme Court, that pulls us all in and
makes us all responsible.
Okay, now we have a new question. איבעיא להו. Ibayu l’hu. שמע
מינה. Shma mina. איבעיא להו. Ibayu l’hu. They asked a new question.
שבט אחד שעשה בהוראת בית דין הגדול, Shevet echad she’asa b’oras beis
din hagadol, one tribe followed the בית דין הגדול, beis din hagadol,
רבי שמעון מי מייתי או לא? Rebbi Shimon mi mayisi o lo?
This was the question we raised because until now רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon has only been talking about seven tribes. What if it's an
individual tribe? Is that enough to say, you know logically you should
say you bring as long as he focuses on individual tribe's responsibility,
but maybe somehow, you know this whole special הלכה only gets implemented
when you have a majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael sinning? תא
שמע, Tashma, come in here. מאן מייתי פר אחד? Man meivi par
echad? רבי שמעון אומר שני פרים. Rebbi Shimon omer shnei parim. We’re
going back to this ברייתא braisa of one and two. Okay. Now
what's the case? במאי עסקינן? Bimai askinan? אילימא דחטאו שבעה, Ileima d’chatu
shiva, שני פרים? shnei parim? שמונה פרים בעי? Shmona parim ba’ei? It
should have been eight if it's your classic example of seven tribes.
אלא דחטא שבט אחד. Ela dechata shevet echad. One tribe sinned. ובמאי?
U’vimai? אילימא בהוראת בית דינו, Ileima b’oras beis dino, if it's its
own local בית דין, רבי שמעון לית ליה, Rebbi Shimon leis lei,
so רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon doesn't hold of the idea of a
local בית דין. אלא בהוראת בית דין הגדול. Ela b’oras beis din
hagadol. The most simplest read of this is it's an idea of
one שבט and he would say you one tribe sinned and it's
one tribe plus the בית דין. So that shows that רבי שמעון’s
Rebbi Shimon. idea applies even in a case of just one tribe
followed it. Okay? So that works very nicely. That's the scenario and
he's saying even if it's just one tribe, that tribe is going
to bring.
One minute.
ותסברא, v'tisbra, now does that make sense? תנא קמא מני, Tanna Kamma
Mani, if that's the case, he's just doing the same ברייתא Braisa
but now focusing on רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon If that's the scenario,
who's this תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that if one tribe sins says
it's just going to be one קרבן? אי רבי מאיר, Ei Rebbi
Meir, הרוב בעי, rubba ba'ei, if it's רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir you
need the majority of the people to be bringing this, the majority
of the people to sin in order to bring. אי רבי יהודה,
Ei Rebbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda הא שאר שבטים
נמי מייתו, ha shar shevatim nami meisu, we've just got through proving
that for רבי יהודה, Yehuda if one tribe sins, all the other
tribes bring as well. So there's no way to read this ברייתא
Braisa that it's just one tribe would sin because then who's the
position that says you only bring one קרבן? For רבי מאיר you're
not bringing any קרבנות korbanos and for רבי יהודה Yehuda. you're bringing
twelve. So the גמרא says no, we could say like we said
before,
הא מני רבי שמעון אלעזר היא, ha mani Rebbi Shimon Elazar hi,
we could move over here, that it's this case of
6+1, 7+1. For some reason רבי שמעון אלעזר Rebbi Shimon Elazar would
say that that's going to, well not for some reason, רבי שמעון
אלעזר Rebbi Shimon Elazar is going to say that that's one
because now he focuses on the בית דין, and רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon is going to say that that is going to be one
for all the tribes plus one for the בית דין. Now why
is it one for all these tribes? You know, I think that
the position that was said a minute ago was a great one,
that maybe this means that it's a scenario where it's one tribe
that sinned and that's the majority of כלל ישראל. Okay, but whatever,
this is the same weird idea we had before if you don't
say that. It's the weird idea before that if, you know, somehow
this, you need some sense of a majority, but if it's only
a majority by one count, then it's only one for all the
tribes. Anyway, because it's possible to read that way, you would not
yet know the answer for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. whether when it
literally is just one tribe, whether that would be sufficient for that
one tribe to bring. Okay, so the גמרא says like this. תא
שמע. Ta shema. וחכמים אומרים לעולם אינו חייב אלא על הוראת בית
דין הגדול.
Vachachamim omrim l'olam eino chayav ela
al horat Beis Din HaGadol. The
end of our משנה, when it says that if a local tribe's
שבט ruled, you're not, you know, that tribe brings. וחכמים Vachachamim say,
no, you need the בית דין הגדול. Beis Din HaGadol. So מאן
חכמים, man Chachamim, who is that חכמים? Chachamim? אילימא רבי מאיר, Ilima
Rebbi Meir, if it's רבי מאיר, so רוב בעי, rubba ba'ei, it's
not just you're missing the ruling of the of the of the
Supreme Court, you're missing the fact that you don't have the majority
of כלל ישראל sinning, right? Because the case, last case of the
משנה was a local tribe, tribe's בית דין, and the local tribe
sinned, and then the חכמים Chachamim come back and say, no, no,
that won't work because you need בית דין הגדול. Beis Din HaGadol.
But for רבי מאיר you don't just need בית דין הגדול, Beis
Din HaGadol, you also need the majority of כלל ישראל to sin.
אלא
לאו רבי שמעון היא. Ella lav Rebbi Shimon hi. The only one
that could be saying that is רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon is saying is, I agree that an individual tribe could
bring, but only with the ruling of בית דין הגדול. Beis Din
HaGadol. So שמע מינה. shema mina. So אלא שמע מינה. ella shema
mina. Okay, so that's a good point. So that's a very good
דיוק. diyuk. The last case in the משנה has רבי יהודה Yehuda
saying a local tribe's בית דין rules, that tribe sins, that's a
קרבן, and then the חכמים Chachamim say, no, I agree that a
local tribe could bring, an individual tribe could bring a קרבן, but
you need it to be a ruling of בית דין הגדול. Beis
Din HaGadol. Okay, so now that we're saying that, that you need
it to be a ruling of בית דין הגדול, Beis Din HaGadol,
you have a ruling of בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol and
a local and a single tribe sinning and you bring a קרבן
even for רבי שמעון and that makes a lot of sense. Once
you're focusing not on the בית דין, once you're focusing on the
sin of the tribe, so therefore even one tribe could go ahead
and bring a קרבן. Okay, excellent. So now the גמרא says like
this. רבי יהודה ורבי שמעון שבט אחד דאיקרי קהל מנא להו? Rebbi
Yehuda v'Rebbi Shimon shevet echad d'ikri kahal mna l'hu? Where do they
have an idea that the קהל kahal can refer to a single
tribe? אמר דכתיב ויעמוד יהושפט בקהל יהודה וירושלים. Amar d'chsiv v'yaamod Yehoshafat
bikhal Yehuda viYerushalayim. Okay, so he stood in the קהל kahal of
יהודה and ירושלים Yerushalayim בבית ה' לפני החצר החדשה b'veis Hashem lifnei
hachatzer hachadasha in the new חצר chatzer of the house of God.
מאי חדשה, Mai chadasha, what was new? אמר רבי יוחנן שחידשו דברים
ואמרו טבול יום לא יכנס במחנה לוייה. Amar Rebbi Yochanan shechidshtu devarim
v'amru tvul yom lo yikanes b'machaneh Leviyah. Okay, they had a new
ruling, somebody had been to the מקוה mikvah that day could not
go onto הר הבית. Har HaBayis. Fine, anyway, but our point is,
it says קהל kahal and it's only talking about יהודה. So you
see the word קהל kahal can be used by a single tribe.
מתיב ליה רב אחא בר יעקב ממאי דילמא שאני ירושלים דהוי נמי
בנימין? Masif lah Rav Acha bar Yaakov mimai dilma shani Yerushalayim d'havi
nami Binyamin? Since it says יהודה and ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ירושלים Yerushalayim also
had a portion of בנימין. Binyamin. Maybe you need two tribes at
least to be called a קהל. kahal. אלא אמר רב אחא בר
יעקב דכתיב ויאמר אלי הנני מפרך והרביתך ונתתיך לקהל עמים. Ella amar
Rav Acha bar Yaakov d'chsiv v'yomer elai hineni mafracha v'hirbisicha u'nesaticha likhal
amim. Okay, so God says to יעקב, Yaakov, the angel says to
יעקב, Yaakov, "Behold I will increase you and and whatever, you know,
make you fruitful and increase you and give you for a קהל
kahal of nations." מאן דעתיד דמתיליד ליה בההיא שעתא, Man d'asid d'misyalid
lei b'hahu shaata, who was about to be born to יעקב Yaakov
when the angel appeared to יעקב? Yaakov? בנימין. Binyamin. So בנימין Binyamin
was the only one who hadn't yet been born. שמע מינה הכי
קאמר רחמנא מיסייד לך השתא קהל אחרינא, Shema mina hachi kaamar Rachmana
misyalid lach hashta kahal achrina, "I am going to give you another
קהל." kahal. So you see that one tribe, ונתתיך לקהל עמים, u'nesaticha
likhal amim, is called a קהל. kahal. אמר ליה רב שישי Amar
lei Rav Shishi אמר ליה רב שישא בריה דרב כהנא Amar leh
Rav Shisha breh deRav Kahana דילמא הכי קאמר ליה רחמנא dilma hachi
ka’amar leh rachmana maybe this is what God was saying to יעקב.
Yaakov. וכי מסיליד לך בנימין v’chi misyaled lach Binyamin when בנימין Binyamin
will be born to you, הוא דהוה י"ב שבטים דמיקרו קהל. hu
d’hava yud beis shvatim d’mikru kahal. נתתיך לקהל עמים nesasicha lekehal amim
means after you get all twelve tribes, all twelve tribes, then you
all, you will be a קהל. kahal. So maybe that’s the idea.
Not that the בנימין Binyamin is a קהל, kahal, all of them
are a קהל. kahal. אמר ליה Amar leh אלא י"ב שבטים איקרו
קהל ela yud beis shvatim ikru kahal י"א שבטים לא איקרו קהל?
yud aleph shvatim lo ikru kahal? No.
That can’t be because everybody would agree that if you have seven
tribes, the majority, that’s a קהל. kahal. So you can't say that
only with all twelve are you a קהל. kahal. So since you
can't read the פסוק pasuk that plus בנימין Binyamin all twelve are
קהל, kahal, you have to read it that בנימין Binyamin himself is
a קהל kahal and you see that an individual tribe is a
קהל. kahal. Excellent. We will stop here.
We still have a few minutes.
I'll read this דיוק. diyuk. What is a דיוק? diyuk?
A דיוק diyuk is like something that you learn from a close
read of